（ターニャ）
第二〇三航空魔導大隊の―
Tanya von Degurechaff,
of the 203rd Aerial Mage Battalion.
ターニャ･フォン･
デグレチャフ少佐であります
（ターニャ）
ゼートゥーア閣下に お取り次ぎを
I need to speak with General Zettour.
（将校）ああ 少佐殿
Oh, Major...
申し訳ありませんが
閣下は現在 外出中です
I'm sorry, but the general is away.
では
ルーデルドルフ閣下を
General Rudersdorf, then.
（将校）失礼しました
I'm sorry.
その… 参謀連は皆様
そろって外出中でして
All the chief strategists are unavailable.
何か重大な会議でも？
Is there some important meeting?
恐らく ビアホールかと
思いますが
I believe they're at the beer hall.
ビアホール？
The beer hall?
皆様 〝勝利の美酒を〞と
叫ばれていましたので
They were shouting about a victory toast.
できれば 自分も
まざりたいところですが
I wish I could join them,
こればかりは… フッ
（将校たち）あ…
but you know how it is...
（レルゲン）
何かあったのか？
Did something happen?
（レルゲン）
デグレチャフ少佐だ
I mean with Major Degurechaff.
いえ 特には…
No, nothing really.
ゼートゥーア閣下に
She wanted to see General Zettour.
お会いしたいとの
ことでしたので―
I told her he's probably at the beer hall.
ビアホールだと
お伝えしましたが
（レルゲン）
デグレチャフ少佐
Major Degurechaff.
Episode Twelve
How to Use a Victory
確か ミルクと砂糖は…
I don't believe you take milk or sugar.
はい 必要ありません
Correct. No, thank you.
Maybe it isn't right, after all.
（レルゲン）やはり違うかね？
Drinking Dallmayr to celebrate our victory.
戦勝記念のドルマイヤーだ
帝室の御用達だぞ
It's what the imperial family drinks.
ゼートゥーア閣下を
訪問されたようだが―
I hear you wanted to see General Zettour.
今回の勝利に
貴官の功績は計り知れない
Your contribution to this
victory was immeasurable.
何か進言があるのなら
忌憚(きたん)のない意見を聞かせてほしい
If you have something you wish to say,
I'd like to hear your unfiltered opinion.
My unfiltered opinion, huh?
忌憚のない意見… ですか
何か？
Is something...
It's true that our forces
have won a splendid victory.
確かに我が軍は
実に見事な勝利を収めました
The entire world has no choice
but to pay heed to our gallantry.
今や世界の誰もが 我が国の雄姿に
瞠目(どうもく)するしかないでしょう
For this one moment,
the Empire's glory and victory may be real.
帝国の勝利と栄光も
この瞬間だけは
本物なのかもしれません
この瞬間？
This one moment?
Victory.
（ターニャ）勝利… それは
何とも魅惑的であります
Such a tempting thing.
Naturally, everyone wants to savor a taste,
誰もが その美酒を口にしたいと
思うのは当然です
しかし なぜ参謀本部は
but why is Strategic HQ
not making use of this victory?
その勝利を
活用なさらないのでしょう？
（ヴァイス）
少佐殿が参謀本部に？
The major went to Strategic HQ?
From the way she was acting,
she might have gone to yell at them.
（ヴィーシャ）あの様子だと
もしかしたら
どなり込んでるのかも…
Well, no need to worry.
（ヴァイス）
まあ 心配は要らんだろう
（ヴィーシャ）
でも いつもと明らかに…
But she's clearly different than usual—
（グランツ）大丈夫ですよ
Don't worry.
I can't imagine the major
breaking the rules.
（グランツ）少佐殿がルール違反を
犯すなんて考えられません
Right now, she's probably
drinking wine in the banquet hall—
（ノイマン）どうせ今頃は
晩さん室でワインでも―
…って それは無理かあ
Well, maybe not.
Anyone have some lotion?
（ケーニッヒ）
誰か塗り薬 持ってないか？
（ケーニッヒ）日焼けしすぎた
（グランツ）ああ 確か―
I got too much sun.
I think there was some in
Warrant Officer Teyanen's stuff.
タイヤネン准尉の持ち物に
ありましたよ
（ヴィーシャ）ハァ…
勝利を活用しない？
Not making use of our victory?
失礼ながら 我らが参謀本部は
勝利のしかたを知っていても
If you'll excuse my saying so,
it seems that our Strategic HQ
knows how to win a victory,
but not how to use one.
勝利の使い方は
ご存じないように思われましたので
What does that mean?
どういう意味だね？
参謀本部の皆様は今
I'm told the members of Strategic HQ
are toasting to victory right now.
勝利の美酒に酔いしれて
おられるそうですね
もちろん 前戦で義務を
十全に果たした将兵たちには―
Of course, the soldiers who did
their duty on the front lines
ひとときの享楽を
謳歌(おうか)する権利もありましょう
have the right to celebrate
a moment's respite.
But if even the officers who should guide
the war's course naively revel in victory,
しかし 戦争指導に当たるべき
上級将校までもが―
無邪気に勝利に
沸き返っているのであれば―
that would be a mistake
and a dereliction of duty.
それは怠惰であり失策
It would be a criminal failure to act.
犯罪的な無為無策と
言うほかありません
少佐 そのぐらいにしておけ
さすがに言葉が過ぎる
Major, enough.
That's going too far.
忌憚のない意見をと
おっしゃられたのは
Lieutenant Colonel, you were the one
who asked my unfiltered opinion.
中佐殿でありますが？
Even if Mars, the god of war,
loves you, that is arrogance.
いくら軍神マルスに
愛されているとはいえ―
さすがに ごう慢だろう
I'm afraid, sir, I don't believe
that God loves me at all.
お言葉ですが
神に愛されているなどとは微塵(みじん)も…
You are an exceptional officer,
gifted with foresight and decisiveness.
（レルゲン）貴官は卓越した
先見性と判断力を有した―
類いまれなる将校だが
But I suppose, at their core,
people do not change.
やはり人間の本性は
変わらないというわけか
貴官の抗命未遂について
西方方面軍より抗議があったそうだ
Western theater forces filed a complaint
about your attempt to disobey orders.
小官は与えられた権限内での
行動をとろうとしたまでです
I simply tried to act within
the authority I've been granted.
（レルゲン）規律違反を犯すような
軍人でないことは分かっている
I know you aren't the kind of soldier
who would disobey orders.
But the authority Strategic HQ gave you
とは言え 参謀本部より
貴官に与えられた権限は
wasn't intended to generate
friction on the front lines.
現場での摩擦を
生むためのものではない
武勲を誇るのは結構だが―
You are free to be proud
of your achievements,
１人で打ち立てたと
思ってもらっては困る
but we cannot have you thinking
you accomplished them alone.
共和国は首都を制圧されたのだ
The Republic has lost its capital.
これ以上の交戦は無意味
有害ですらある
Any further resistance is meaningless.
And would be harmful, in fact.
What reason is there to continue the war?
この先も戦争を続けようとする
理由が どこにある？
A modern state uses its military
to impose its will via violence.
近代国家において
軍とは国家の暴力装置だ
国家自体を犠牲にしてまで
戦い続けるなど―
Sacrificing the nation itself to
continue the fight is madness.
狂気の沙汰としか言えまい
You are completely correct.
いかにも そのとおりです
であれば 何故 貴官は
戦争が続くとの主張を？
Then why do you say that
the war will continue?
せん越ながら申し上げますに―
If I may be permitted to give my opinion...
Generals Zettour and Rudersdorf
are logical pragmatists,
ゼートゥーア閣下や
ルーデルドルフ閣下は―
政治と軍事に優れた
合理的なプラグマティスト
highly skilled in political
and military matters.
They are great soldiers.
偉大なる軍人です
この点 中佐殿も同類であられる
As are you, Lieutenant Colonel.
Our Strategic HQ is a powerful
fortress of logic and knowledge.
論理と知識の牙城―
それが我が帝国の
参謀本部であります
そのために誰もが
合理的な考えの下―
And therefore, due to logical reasoning,
戦争の終結を信じておられる
everyone believes the war is at its end.
But it must be said that
this rationale is incomplete.
しかし… それは不完全な合理性と
言わざるをえません
不完全な… 合理性？
Incomplete...?
The members of Strategic HQ
are far too rational.
（ターニャ）参謀本部の皆様は
あまりに合理的すぎるのです
And thus, they have
completely missed the point.
故に 完全に
見落としておられるのです
Rationalism isn't the only thing
that drives human action.
人間という存在が
合理性だけでは動かない―
We are foolish creatures...
愚かな生き物であるということを
貴官は 我々人類が―
Are you saying that humans are
still beasts, lacking in reason?!
いまだ理性を欠いた獣だとでも
言いたいのかね
If I may be permitted to speak freely,
then that is completely correct.
（ターニャ）語弊を恐れずに
申し上げるならば―
まったくもって そのとおりかと
And what evidence do you
have for this statement?
（レルゲン）
何を根拠に そう言い切れる！
History.
（ターニャ）歴史であります
Though I mean my own history.
と言っても 私自身の歴史
My personal experience.
個人的な経験ではありますが
聞かせてもらおう
Tell me.
I have seen the eyes of men,
burning with hatred.
（ターニャ）私は見てきました
憎しみにとらわれた
燃えるような人々の目を
I have seen the moment
when my talented men
優秀な部下が怒りに身を任せ
冷静さを失った瞬間を
gave in to anger and lost their reason.
I have seen a chain of revenge,
憎悪のみに突き動かされる―
driven only by hate.
復讐(ふくしゅう)の連鎖を
そして小官は気づいたのです
And so, I realized...
No, perhaps it's more accurate
to say that I remembered.
いや… 気づいたと言うより―
思い出したと
言うべきかもしれません
私は以前 合理主義に対する
狂気的な反発をー
I have personally experienced
an insane reaction against rationalism.
身をもって経験しました
いかに近代化が進もうとも―
No matter how much we modernize,
no matter how social norms affect us,
いかに社会規範が
浸透しようとも―
人間は時として合理性よりも―
humans are foolish creatures
who sometimes prize feelings over reason.
感情を優先する
愚かな存在であるということを
憎悪にとらわれた人間は
A human being who's overcome
with hatred will keep struggling,
打算も 合理性も 損得さえ抜きに
どこまでも抗い続けます
without regard for self-interest or reason,
regardless of what they may lose or gain.
That is why I cannot help but to speak up.
だからこそ 小官は申し上げずには
いられないのです
We should not become intoxicated
by a temporary victory!
我々は かりそめの勝利になぞ
酔いしれるべきではない
All flames of hatred
憎悪の火は全て
消し去らねばならないと
must be extinguished.
E-Excuse me.
（将校）し… 失礼します
This information is still being verified,
（将校）まだ 調査中の
情報ではありますが―
南方大陸で
共和国軍残党に動きが…
but remnants of the Republican Army
are active on the southern continent.
Unified Year 1925, August 10
As a freedom-loving Republican citizen...
（ド･ルーゴ）
私は自由を愛する―
Southern Continent, Chiers Military Port
共和国市民として―
As a proud Republican citizen, I swear
誇りある共和国市民として誓う！
I shall not lower my weapon
until the day of victory!
（ド･ルーゴ）勝利の日まで
決して 武器は下ろさぬと！
我が戦友諸君も その力を
貸してくれようとしている！
My comrades-in-arms
lend me their power, as well.
The fate of the world
rests on our shoulders.
我々に 世界の命運が
懸かっているのだ！
And thus, I now...
よって 私は今
祖国を代表する
自由共和国の一員として
As a member of the Free Republic,
on behalf of my homeland,
I swear I will fight the Empire
帝国への徹底抗戦を―
ここに 宣言する！
until the end!
Meanwhile, Imperial Capital Berun
Didn't the Republic fall?
（男性）共和国は
落ちたんじゃなかったのか？
Damn it!
（男性）クソッ
軍のヤツらは何やってんだ！
What are they doing?!
（女性）
ヨハン もうずっと連絡がないの
Johann hasn't gotten in touch at all.
（女性）
まだ 戦争は続くのかしら…
Will the war keep going?
This is the Imperial Army with
your three o'clock war update.
（ラジオ音声）帝国陸軍発表
午後３時の戦局情報です
（男性）
早く南方大陸攻めろよ
We should go attack
the southern continent now.
The remnants of the Republican Army,
led by General Du Lugo,
（ラジオ音声）ド･ルーゴ将軍率いる
共和国軍の残党は―
（男性）これほど
長期化していいのか？
Is it okay to let this drag out?
逃亡先の南方大陸にて
自由共和国を称し―
are calling themselves the "Free Republic."
"Remnants of the Republic
Rise on the Southern Continent"
They declare they intend to
fight our Empire to the end.
我が帝国軍に対する
徹底抗戦を宣言しました
Imperial Army, 203rd Aerial Mage Battalion Quarters
（グランツ）フゥ…
How long will this go on?
一体 いつまで
こんなことが続くんでしょうか
次のクリスマスまでには
戦争も終わる
I heard the war would be
over by next Christmas.
そう聞いていたのにな
At least, that's what I was told.
In the end, we'll barely get any break.
結局 休みもほとんどなし
また いつもの最前線で
Back to the front lines like normal,
泥だらけになって
冷めたごはんかあ…
covered in mud and eating cold food?
（ヴィーシャたち）ハァ…
（ヴァイス）“至難の戦場”
"Extremely difficult battle. Little pay."
“わずかな報酬 剣林弾雨(けんりんだんう)の日々”
"Spend your days in combat
and unfathomable danger."
“絶えざる危険”
"If you return alive,
“生還の暁には
名誉と称賛を得る”
you'll receive honor and glory."
The words on the recruitment poster?
大隊の募集要項ですか？
Yeah.
ああ 最後の文句以外は
真実だったな
Except for the last part, it was all true.
You seem upset.
（ルーデルドルフ）浮かない顔だな
Have you still not sobered up
from your first drink in a while?
まだ久しぶりの酒が
抜けてないのか？
I'm told this Free Republican Army
is steadily expanding its forces.
自由共和国軍とやらは
着々と戦力を拡大中だそうだ
Survivors from the Allied Kingdom and the Entente Alliance
協商連合の生き残りや
連合王国も合流し始めたらしい
have begun to join them.
本土で進んでいた講和の件が
白紙撤回されるのも当然だな
The peace treaty being
drafted back home
has been sent back to
the drawing board, obviously.
（ゼートゥーア）結局のところ―
Ultimately, the problem is our failure
to defeat all of the enemy's forces.
敵を倒しきれなかったことが
問題であろう
こうなった以上
南方に派兵するしかあるまい
Now, our only choice is to
send troops south.
Our military is army-based...
（ゼートゥーア）
我々は陸軍国家だ
Any expedition crossing the sea will
put a severe strain on our system.
海を渡った外征は戦力基盤に
相当な負荷を及ぼす
We must send as few troops as possible.
規模は最小限に
とどめねばならんぞ
少数精鋭か
では 例の大隊に出てもらおう
A small, elite force, huh?
Let's use that battalion, then.
（ゼートゥーア）ああ そうだな…
Yes, you're right.
（ルーデルドルフ）ん？ 何だ？
What?
No, I don't think it's anything.
（ゼートゥーア）
いや… 何もないはずだ
We're friends here.
我々の仲だ 何が言いたい
What do you want to say?
Are we doing something wrong?
（ゼートゥーア）我々は 何かを
間違っていないだろうか
The deployment to the south
（ゼートゥーア）南方作戦とて―
assumes that no other country joins the war.
これ以上の参戦国が増えないことを
前提にした計画だ
If another does...
もし仮に 更なる国が
戦争に参加するとなると…
If any other countries intervene in the war...
Unified Year 1925, August 15
Ocean Waters Near the Southern Continent
（ターニャ）戦火の絶えない
呪われた世界で―
In a cursed world,
engulfed by flames of war,
there was a nation known as the Empire.
その国は“帝国”と呼ばれていた
With its vast military power,
帝国は絶大な軍事力―
talented strategists, and high mobility,
it overwhelmed the Dukedom of Dakia,
卓越した戦術と
優れた機動力により―
ダキア公国 協商連合
共和国を圧倒
the Entente Alliance, and the Republic.
Threats to its safety were
removed, one after the next,
安全保障上の脅威を次々に退け
誰もが随喜(ずいき)した
and everyone was overjoyed.
But that is why they could not imagine
だが それゆえ
彼らは想像しえなかった
how much the surrounding countries feared
帝国が強大無比な覇権を
大陸中央に確立するという事実―
the creation of a massive power
in the continent's center.
そのことに対する
周辺諸国の根本的な恐怖を…
I can't believe it...
（将校）いやはや 信じられんな
（将校）まったく… 往生際の悪い
Jeez, they should give up already.
The Empire went to such lengths to
display the sharpness of its sword,
（ターニャ）帝国は 自らが握った
剣の鋭さを誇示するあまり―
その剣に対する恐怖を
想像しえないでいたのだ
it was incapable of imagining
the terror that its sword inspired.
Southern Continent, Chiers Military Port
Of course, everyone wants peace.
無論 誰もが
平和を願っている
そう あれかしと…
So, to protect peace,
they take up their guns
そえゆえ皆 平和を守るために
銃を取り―
and thrust themselves
into battle, hoping to achieve it.
平和を願って戦いに身を投じる
Allied Kingdom Capital Londinium
So that this cruel war would end,
（ターニャ）過酷な戦争を
終わらせるべく―
帝国以外の誰もが願っていた
everyone except the Empire wished
帝国という邪悪な敵が
この地より撃滅されんことを
for the evil enemy called the Empire
to be eliminated from the world.
Near the Federation's Border
かくして
何たる矛盾だろうか
Could there be any greater paradox?
Ironically, their desire for peace
皮肉なことに
平和への願いによって―
戦争は鎮まるどころか
激化の一途をたどっていく
caused the war's intensification,
rather than its end.
Somewhere in the U.S., Army Recruiting Office
It's true that
（徴兵担当官）
確かに 合衆国軍は現在
the U.S. is presently recruiting
volunteer deployment units
友好国に派遣される義勇派兵部隊の
志願を募っていますが…
to be sent to allied countries.
But you're at the minimum age
for volunteers, Mary Sioux.
メアリー･スーさん
あなたは志願できる最低年齢です
You can take more time to decide.
もっと じっくり考えてから
決断をしても遅くは…
No, I volunteer.
（メアリー）いえ 志願します
We're very happy you feel that way,
心意気は
大変うれしく思いますが―
戦場に出れば
ケガをするかもしれませんし―
but if you go to the battlefield,
you may be hurt or even killed.
命を落とすことだって…
覚悟はできています
I'm prepared for that.
（徴兵担当官）お母様…
I'm sure that your mother
and your late father
それに亡くなられた
お父様も きっと
would want for you to live
in a peaceful place.
あなたが平和な地で
過ごされることを
願っておられるはずですよ
I know that.
それは分かっています
But that's why
でも だからこそ
I want to do what I can!
私は自分のできることを
したいのです
To protect that peace!
その平和を守るために！
You won't change your mind, will you?
（徴兵担当官）
決意は変わらないようですね
I understand.
分かりました
では 志願に際し宣誓を！
Then make your declaration
as you volunteer.
I declare that for sake of
the peace I must protect,
宣誓！ 私は守るべき
平和のため―
何より 大切な家族のため
and for sake of the family I love,
I will give my whole power!
力の全てを費やします！
To make a world where no one else
has to experience the sadness...
もう二度と 帝国によって
家族を失う悲しみが―
of losing their family to the Empire.
繰り返されない世界を
つくるために！
And to enact God's justice!
そして… 神の正義をなすために！
I swear by my good heart,
which believes in the Lord!
主を信じる
善良なる心に誓って
May the Lord's grace be with me!
神のご加護があらんことを！
AH RA LA OH LA
Don't go away nigeba wa nai
Don't go away, there's nowhere to run!
Oh why? You're crying warae kurue
Oh why? You're crying... laugh, go mad!
Coming up, coming up...
aa, satsui no me
Ahh, eyes full of bloodlust
iki na emono takaburu takaburu
Faced with fresh prey, getting aroused... aroused...
Not enough, not enough...
mada sono inochi yuetsu ni tari wa shinai
We haven't taken enough lives to attain joy!
We all are the jingoes oh oh oh
kemonojimita yoku o musabore
Indulge in your beastly desire!
We are in the jungle oh oh oh
saa kiba o toge shi no kazu o kisoou ah
Come, sharpen your fangs... and let's see who can kill more... ah!
We all are the jingoes oh oh oh..
We are in the jungle oh oh oh...
Attention, everyone!
（ヴァイス）総員 傾注！
A message from the battalion commander!
大隊長より訓示！
諸君 やれ停戦だ出撃だと
まったく上も勝手なものだな
Everyone, we've gone from
an armistice to a sortie.
The brass just does whatever it wants.
But since it's our job, we have no choice.
だが 仕事である以上は
やむをえん
命令に従い
敵をたたき潰さねばなるまい
We must follow our orders
and crush the enemy.
とは言え 今や世界の全てが
我々の敵だ
But now, our enemy is the whole world.
There's no way to avoid a cruel war,
過酷な戦闘は避けられようもなく
泥沼の戦いに終わりは見えない
and no end to how long we must fight.
That is why I want to say once more...
だからこそ 諸君らには
改めて伝えておきたい
If there is a God who rules this world,
この世をつかさどる神が
いるとすれば
it is a stern, solemn,
どこまでも厳格で
限りなく善良
and infinitely good being.
あまりにも偉大な存在であろう
A being that is far too great...
神とやらは 非情な運命ばかりを
突きつけてくる
God keeps forcing us to
confront these cruel fates.
As if those were the rules of this world.
それが 世界に課せられた
ルールのようだ
We could only deploy
two divisions and a support unit.
（将校）派遣できたのは
たったの２個師団と支援部隊のみ
（将校）共和国の現地警備隊ですら
対抗可能な数です
Even the Republic's local security
force could handle that number!
If their allies start sending troops, too...
（将校）ここに同盟国の派兵も
加わるとなると…
Orders for troops on the ground?
（ゼートゥーア）
現場への指示は？
既に通達済みだ
Already sent.
Upon arrival, our forces will maintain
constant mobility at all times.
我が軍は到着と同時に
徹底した機動戦を展開
The enemy will split up to attack us,
and we will defeat them in detail.
分散進撃してくる敵を
各個撃破する計画です
その先鋒(せんぽう)となるのが
Major Degurechaff's
203rd Battalion will take point.
デグレチャフ少佐の率いる
二〇三大隊
（将校）しかし あの少佐とて
この程度の戦力では…
But with a force this size...
Even the major...
I believe that is quite
a reasonable opinion.
確かに
ごもっともな意見だと思います
（ターニャ）そこでだ
私は今ここに 改めて宣言する
Thus, I declare once more...
おお 神よ！
Oh, God...
I'll slice you into tiny pieces
and feed you to the pigs!
貴様を切り刻んで
豚のエサにでもしてやると！
But there's nothing...
ですが 何一つ… 何一つとして
心配はご無用でしょう
nothing to worry about at all.
Our battlefield is no place
for that piece of shit God!
クソッタレの神に
我らが戦場は不似合いだ！
I think it's time we
took over God's work.
今こそ神の仕事を
肩代わりしてやろうではないか！
我ら将兵のあるうちは
我々が神に取って代わるのだ！
We soldiers will take God's place.
We'll put the arrogant ass, God, out of a job!
ごう慢な神とやらを
失業させてやれ！
Yes, ma'am!
If I may speak freely...
（レルゲン）
せん越ながら申し上げますと―
She is a monster in the form
あれは 幼女の皮をかぶった―
化物です！
of a little girl!
All right, troops...
では 戦友諸君…
It is time for war!
戦争の時間だ！